Finding Aid for Letters, Documents, & Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Letters, Documents, and Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
  - 1852 November 2. B[enjamin] H[arris] Kinney ALS to J[ohn] C[hester] Buttre; Worcester, Massachusetts, 2 pages; Discusses Buttre producing an engraving of Kinney's of Ethan Allen from a daguerreotype. Notes the difficulties of producing a good daguerreotype of such a large statue. Sending two original daguerreotypes in different lights [not present].
  - 1852 December 22. Jona[than] E. Ferre ALS to Nephew; Agawam, [Massachusetts], 4 pages; Acknowledges their differing views on the presence of "ministering spirits." Ferre believes that "we have both good and evils spirits constantly exerting an influence upon our minds." Influence of evil spirits over the thoughts of all is spiritual warfare, as written of in the Bible. Discusses the existence of guardian angels. Gives an account of a pious young woman receiving communications from her deceased grandmother and aunt, her guardian angels. "She is strictly forbidden to have any intercourse with the rapping spirits of the day being told that they are disorderly. She is in perfect freedom to make any disclosures she pleases." The family prefers this news not be made public. Men of the Primitive Church had similar gifts. Notes local regulars at Spiritualist meetings.
  - 1852 December 23-26. S. G. Haley ALS to Maria (sister); Hooksett, [New Hampshire], 4 pages; Letter from a teacher to his sister. Unable to follow her advice about limiting his interactions with women, as his teaching requires it. "... how can I get rid of speaking to the girls here, who attend my school, and who are real smart, pretty, fascinating girls, and, old enough when they improve every opportunity to speak to me?" Promises not to attend any more balls. He lists the names and ages of all of his students, underlining young women's names. Describes the daily class schedule. He also expresses how much he misses home, how Hooksett is a "rum hole" and describes his attitudes towards loud children and improvements he needs to make as a teacher. See also Haley letter dated January 14, 1853.
  - 1852 October 11-1854 October 30. 5 ADsS; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 23 pages [total]; Regarding the court case of E. C. and P. H. Warren vs. James Hunter and Bros, concerning the Hunter's pollution of Mill Creek (Pennsylvania) with chemical wastes, infringing on the water rights of the Warren's paper mill. Includes a letter from attorney Thomas Wharton to James Hunter & brothers warning them to desist from depositing dyes and chemicals into the river; two copies of testimony given by Frederick A. Genth on September 16, 1854, concerning his chemical analysis of the river water; short statements from various witnesses; and a record of filing Genth's deposition. Case tried by Thomas I. and Henry Wharton.
  - 1853 January 2-[1908]. Isaac Pitman 8 items; various, 14 pages total; 8 items related to Isaac Pitman: 3 Shorthand ALs written in Pitman's hand, dated January 2, 1853; January 26, 1859; and January 18, 1886. One TL transcription of the 1853 shorthand letter to Benn Pitman. One ALS Photographic Institute Company postcard from Benn Pitman to Alex Hill [September 4, 1908]. 2 printed pamphlets regarding Pitman's shorthand and life. 1 photogravure of Isaac Pitman, 1890.
  - 1853 January 14. S. G. Haley ALS to Geo[rge] H. Haley (brother); Hooksett, [New Hampshire], 4 pages; Letter from a teacher to his brother, regarding his homesickness. Grateful for George's advice about girls. He writes out lines from a poem that he composed, "Old Kearsarge." He talks about going to Concord the next week and relays information regarding current events - particularly dealing with family matters. See also Haley letter dated December 23, 1852.
  - 1853 February 25. W[illiam] McLain ALS to Horatio Seymour; Colonization Rooms, Washington, [D.C.], 1 page; Seymour has been elected to the position of Vice President of the American Colonization Society. Forwarding a copy of the Annual Report [not included].
  - 1853 March 6. Elijah Counts ALS to Isaiah D. Counts; s.l., 2 pages; Comments on the construction of a railroad from Uniontown, Pennsylvania, to Logansport or Peru, Indiana, and efforts to get the line to pass through certain towns. The railroad may pass close to Counts's house. Notes prices of nearby land; encourages his brother to buy soon.
  - 1853 March 8. J.M. Carlisle, Rich[ar]d S. Coxe, Jos. H. Bradley, W. Redin, J. Hellen, Walter [ ], and Jno. Marbury ALS to Franklin Pierce; Wash[ington, D.C.], 1 page; Members of the Bar of Washington, D.C., recommend Philip Barton Key (1818-1859) as U.S. Attorney. Signed by J. M. Carlisle, Rich[ar]d S. Coxe, Jos. H. Bradley, W. Redin, J. Hellen, Walter S. [Con?], and Jno. Marbury.
  - 1853 June 17. Hamilton Fish ALS to Colin M[acrae] Ingersoll; New York [City, New York], 1 page; Requests information on the organization of the faculty at Yale. Lists seven queries regarding wages, hours, terms, hiring requirements, privileges, etc.
  - 1853 June 26. Geo[rge] C. Brundage ALS to "friend"; Gibson, 2 pages; Has been busy, having "the whole management of the farm." Includes news concerning mutual acquaintances. Discusses farming business and offers marriage advice. "Don't think of anything else, keep poking about the rubbish of the world till you have stirred up a gem worth possessing in the shape of a w.i.f.e." Encourages him to marry soon and emphasizes the positive benefits of marriage.
  - 1853 July 1-[1860 December]. Cyrus Lukens AMs; s.l., 82 pages; Diary of daily weather and events. Dates recorded in the Quaker style. Notes the anniversary of the "Great Fire 1850," death of Gen. Taylor, the reception of General Pierce, the opening of the Crystal Palace, eclipses, accidents, parades, exhibitions, social visits, the "U.S. National Show," and fires, including a deadly one at "Welch's Circus, Chinese Museum." In 1857, notes the loss of the S.S. Central America and a "Great run upon the banks" leading to the "suspension of spiecie payment." Notes the anniversary of the Pennsylvania Literary Society. Records the 1860 Presidential election and Lincoln's majority in Philadelphia and Pennsylvania. "So Ends my Diary Book. I being in Council Bluffs, Iowa"
  - 1853 September 21. Thomas and Mary Owens ALS to Richard Owens; Cincinnati, Ohio, 3 pages; Letter to parents in Welsh; concerns business matters in part.
  - 1853 November 05. J[ohn] A[rchibald] Campbell ALS to Duncan G. Campbell; Mobile, [Alabama], 7 pages; John Campbell's advice to his son before his son leaves to study "mathematical science" in Germany. Campbell mentions the importance of "patient persevering study," choosing "honorable & moral" friends, and not making any "extravagant expenditure" or partaking in diversions. Advises him about not interfering with German government or laws.
  - 1853 November 25. Sam[ue]l F.B. Morse ALS; Poughkeepsie, [New York], 1 page; Responds to a request for his autograph. "So small a favor as my autograph cannot be denied, and I therefore comply with your request, trusting that your life so recently commenced may be devoted to the cause of Him who preserves it, and to Him who died to save you." With: Engraved portrait of Samuel F.B. Morse, 1867, from the original painting by [Alonzo] Chappel.
  - 1853 November 29. F[rancis] Wayland ALS to N. Ropes; Providence, [Rhode Island], 4 pages; Has been busy and seldom in Boston. Comments on the news from Crimea of suffering among the troops. "How horrible is the news from the Crimea The amount of death by disease and slaughter is awful." Emphasizes the need for Christianity.
  - 1853 December 16. Henry H. Sage ALS to [Alonzo Dwight] Blodgett; Buffalo, [New York], 2 pages; Comical letter detailing Sage's "request & requirements" in order for him to perform at Blodgett's "Grand Concerto." "First Being in delicate health I should require the exclusive services of not more than seven colored male servants, with a female hairdresser to prepare my jetty locks for each entertainment." Requests two fine hotel rooms, restorative food and drink to counteract the heat, waiting maids for his "favorite poodle and two beautiful grey Tom-cats," as well as additional freight cars to help his pianist, Signor J. Randolpho Blogetti, cart his baggage and luxurious mustache. Remarks on payment. Written on illustrated J. Sage & Sons stationery, including an image of two cherubs playing a flute and reading, accompanied by a printed J. Sage & Sons envelope. "Publishers of Sheet Music & Wholesale & Retail Dealers in Piano Fortes & Musical Merchandise."
  - 1853 September 17 - 1854 February 4. Lizzie Higgins Diary; [near Norwalk, Ohio], 27 pages; Manuscript diary beginning in Washington, D.C. Describes her journey by railroad through Baltimore, Pennsylvania, and Ohio. Remarks on religion, social visits, health. Tells of a visit with Grandma Hoyt, who told them "of her being taken prisoner by the Indians & of their painting her up and telling her that she was a pretty little squaw and of her filling her pockets with bullets to kill the Indians, and crying when her sister threw them away because they made her so heavy. She telling her sister that now she had no way to kill the Indians." Comments on spirit rappings and mediums and her anxiety that participating in them are contrary to the Bible.
  - 1854 April 12. John Smith ADS to Samuel Nelson; G[reat] S[alt] L[ake] City, [Utah], 1 page; Patriarchal blessing from John Smith, Patriarch of the Mormon Church.
  - 1854 April 22. C[aleb] Cushing ALS to Brantz Mayer; Washington, [D.C.], 1 page; Cushing (then U.S. Attorney-General) thanks historian Brantz Mayer for his letter and "two accompanying discourses." He comments on English history and on the Michael Cresap-James Logan affair, probably in reference to two 1851 Mayer works: "Mexico, Aztec, Spanish and Republican" and "Tah-Gah-Jute: or Logan and Captain Michael Cresap."
  - 1854 September 15. W[illiam] A. Stearns ALS to Mr. Pollock; Cambridgeport, [Massachusetts], 1 page; Has no copies of the discourse requested by Mr. Pollock, but believes that it may be obtained from the publisher, James Munroe & Co. Sending "a copy of a sermon, in Commemoration of Daniel Webster" [not present].
  - 1854 September 21. J[onathan] K[elsey] Burr ALS to "Sister"; Burlington, New Jersey, 4 pages; Comments on prevailing "fever and ague" in the region and the end of the cholera season. Describes a camp meeting at which Burr (and 11 others) preached. "Communion with nature, on the Camp Ground after a long draught, means the breathing an atmosphere surcharged with dust - the Endurance of heat that would startle a Thermometer if had ventured there - and many other things that partake very much of the nature of inconveniences." Notes the emotional reactions of attendees.
  - [1854?]. Fanny Kemble ALS; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Arranging details for her upcoming reading in Baltimore of Shakespeare's Merry Wives of Windsor.
  - 1855 January 30. Josiah Quincy ALS to M[ary] A. Quincy; No. 1, Beacon Hill Place, [Boston, Massachusetts], 1 page; Wishes her a belated happy New Year. "It is never too late to follow the impulses of the heart, which time may strengthen, but cannot weaken nor to recall an opportunity, lost by your absence, to express the best affections toward you of your Grandfather."
  - 1855 May 9. Edward Everett ALS to Thomas Talbot, J.G.D. Stearns, John Baldwin, W[illia]m H. Odiorne, Thomas B. Edwards; Boston, [Massachusetts], 3 pages; Declining an invitation to the "celebration of the Second Centennial Anniversary of the Incorporation of Billerica [Massachusetts]" "There are but a few of the ancient towns of Massachusetts, whose early history contains a fuller record of the stirring & trying scenes of border life." Comments on Indian attacks on the town; "men, women, & children were killed or carried into a captivity worse than death. But the great and good men of those times relied upon a wisdom & strength beyond those of man; & possessed the fortitude & resolution which carried them through the dreadful ordeal. They left a precious inheritance to their children."
  - [1855] June 4. W[illia]m H[ickling] Prescott ALS to [John Stetson Barry]; [Boston, Massachusetts], 4 pages; Thanking Stetson for sending him a copy of his History of Massachusetts. His progress in the book is slow due to his failing eyesight. Despite this, Prescott offers a lengthy critique of both the content and the writing itself. "The subject you have chosen is a noble one... A person, to do justice to our pilgrim fathers, should have some of their blood in his veins... The manner in which you have inlaid your narrative with brief extracts from your original authorities shows how freely you have drawn from the best sources of information & has the advantage of carrying the reader back more vividly to the scenes you describe..."
  - [18]55 July 16. Edward Everett ALS to [George William] Childs & [Robert E.] Peterson; Boston, [Massachusetts], 4 pages; Edward Everett declines to review or offer his opinion on a volume sent to him previously by Childs & Peterson. The demands on his time and controversies attendant upon unfavorable reviews prevents him from undertaking such work. "I accordingly formed a rule to myself more than thirty years ago, not to express opinions of books except under peculiar circumstances, which would require or warrant an exception..."
  - 1855 July 26. John [T?] Huntington ALS to Charley; Cape May, [New Jersey], 3 pages; Huntington amusingly describes social life at the Mount Vernon Hotel where he is vacationing. "Last night there was a ‘Hop' in the Dining-Room which is 412 feet long, & such an array of bare-skinned dresses & beauty I never did see. Alas for the pomps & vanities of this remarkable world! What are we coming to?"
  - 1855 October 19. Susan B. Anthony ALS to Mrs. C. M. Crowley; Rochester, [Massachusetts?], 2 pages; Encourages Mrs. Crowley to work for the cause of women's rights and to enlist a woman in Cattaraugus County to canvas the area. "Cattaraugus ought to produce one woman with the requisite will- She has hundreds with the talent." She encloses printed materials to assist her in her efforts. Enclosures: One blank petition for the Senate and Assembly of New York to enfranchise women and one printed circular for insertion in local newspapers, "Justice to Women," advertising an upcoming convention and featuring an illustration of a train of shoes with an "E.A. Miller" banner. Crowley lived in Randolph, New York. Envelope stamped Worcester, Massachusetts.
  - [18]55 November 21. Geo[rge] Sumner ALS to Clinton C[assady? ]; New York [City, New York], 4 pages; Received his recipient's "interesting, clear and eloquent address on the 4th July last," which Sumner believes is sound for its strict neutrality and interest in "real liberty in Europe." Has finished writing his lecture on "the changes which education is working on the masses in Europe" Hopes the example of American education "may help progress & liberty, without the aid of gunpowder & fillibusters." Dedicates a portion of the lecture to school systems in Holland and Ireland Plans to return to Boston.
  - 1855 December 3. John Tyler ALS to M. D. Phillips; Sherwood Forest [Plantation, Virginia], 1 page; Declines an invitation to deliver a lecture. "My lectures are never attended with any charge but are entirely voluntary and for the benefit of the Institutions or associations before which they are delivered."
  - 1855 December 31 - 1857 July 19. AMs, 40 pages [total]; Journal of a surveyor in Princeton, Illinois, with an account of his journey from (and return to) Lowell, Massachusetts. Describes landscape, passing through Canada and Detroit. Comments on his surveying work, religion, books he read, local education. Notes local hostility to the road surveys, with some residents threatening bodily harm. Witnessed "two young ladies... kissing each other frantically" and believes Dr. Sewall needs a wife, "for he hugs me outrageously nights." Comments on courtship and women, political meetings and the "Kansas matter," Fourth of July celebrations. Criticizes young women's behavior and comments on their appearance. Attended a sermon on the "Woman's sphere." Suffered from a lingering illness. On his return journey, visited a manufactory in Troy, New York. Includes an 11-page speech on common schools.
  - 1855-1857. William Vandergrift Various, 8 items; 2 ALsS, 2 ADfs, 2 Docs, 1 Memo, 1 Account. regarding Vandergrift's building activities, with two plans for schoolhouses at Newportville, Pennsylvania. [Originals located in the William R. Vandergriff papers]
  - 1856 Januray 28. James Guthrie DS to A[lexander] H[amilton] Bowman; Treasury Dept. [Washington, D.C.], 1 page; Informs Bowman that he has been selected by the President as a commissioner to meet at the Philadelphia mint to test "the correctness of the Assay of the coinage of the U States"
  - 1856 April 16. Henry D[ilworth] Gilpin ALS to Henry S[tephens] Randall; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 4 pages; Will send a volume of James Madison's letters for Randall's use, "if you think the safety of the Express can be relied upon." Praises Randall's biographical work on Thomas Jefferson (which would be published in 1858). Comments on how quickly original sources can vanish. Wondering if the Documentary History of New York has continued.
  - [1856] October 17. H[arriet] B[eecher] Stowe ALS to Mr. Thomas; London, [England], 3 pages; Hopes to visit her anti-slavery friends in Scotland in the spring. "A great crisis my dear Sir is hurrying on, and I am much comforted by the deep & brotherly interest which England feels for & with us who are called to suffer for & with the cause of freedom-- When I say us I mean the suffering brave of America who stand now as once your covenanters did for a sacred cause."
  - 1857 April 11. A[mbrose] E. Burnside ALS to Mrs. Green; Bristol, Rhode Island, 1 page; Notification that he will no longer rent her house. Originally laid in notebook of the Bristol, Rhode Island Maternal Association of St. Michael's Church (Blandina Diedrich Collection).
  - 1857 May 30. J[acob] Gideon ALS to "the President"; Washington, [D.C.], 1 page; Recommending John S. Edwards for the position of Marshal, District of Columbia.
  - 1857 July 7. Thomas C. Donn and J. H. Goddard ADS (copy); [Washington, D.C.], 2 pages; Copy of the October 23, 1856 contract binding 16-year-old orphan Patrick Lynch as an apprentice to Michael McDermott, coach maker. With an amendment dated July 7, 1857: Letitia McDermott, widow of Michael McDermott, transfers her right to Patrick Lynch, apprentice.
  - 1857 August 23. J. D. Gontz ALS to Mr. Logan; Galena, [Illinois], 3 pages; Describes Galena, commenting on lead ore in the region. Traveled from Johnstown [New York] to Galena by stage and steamer. "...but when we arrived on the Mississipa it was raging at its greatest hight i have seen farmes and Houses and a few small villages that the watter was up to the seckond stories of the houses and the inhabitants were forced to fly to the mountains and in camp out until the water would fall and the they would get back to their homes again"
  - 1857 September 2. J[ames] Hamilton ALS to W[illiam] W. Corcoran; Newport, Rhode Island, 6 pages; Urging Corcoran to engage in speculation of Texas lands, especially for coal and salt. Hopes to meet with Corcoran to discuss "the details of your proposed agency for paying the Texas Debt." Contrasts coal mining in Texas to the northern states.
  - 1857 November 25. W[illia]m H. Ireland, Jr. ALS to M.A.W. Man[ ]; New York, [New York], 10 pages; Thanksgiving greetings; is sending a group of verses to brighten the recipient's holiday. Includes 9 pages of rhyming verses and musical score to sing them by. Describes in detail a steamer trip to New York, then to Perth Amboy, New Jersey, accompanied by a dog. The verses include 23 pen & ink illustrations, including: turkey, a man dressing, Steamboat Sylvan Shore, men taunting his dog, mishaps on the streets of New York, African American ticket salesman, ticket booths, life preservers, ports, stagecoach, tree, woman playing the piano, man preparing for bed, etc.
  - 1857 December 10. Alex[ande]r H. H. Stuart ALS to J.E. Peyton; Richmond, [Virginia], 1 page; Comments on Republican politics. "If we can only persuade the Republicans to give up their sectional organization, & the conservative portion of them to unite with the Whigs & Americans, under the common denigration of ‘opposition', ‘People's' or ‘National Union' party, we can, undoubtedly, carry the election of 1860, provided we have a national candidate."
  - [ca. 1857?]. Doc.; [Massachusetts?], 1 page; Manuscript sketch of a school house. Floor plan and facade elevation. Pen and ink, with watercolor. [Located in Oversize Manuscripts]
  - 1858 February 12. W[illia]m P. M[ason], Jr. ALS to W[illia]m P. Mason; Vienna, [Austria], 8 pages; Describes pre-Lenten balls and parties in "southern Germany." Emperor and Empress in attendance at a grand ball. Comments on clothing, dancing, women, and a daguerreotype. The Baroness "is persuaded that I own a gold-mine or two, with much of the western country, & innumerable negroes, & that it was by some unexplicable providence that I am not black myself..."
  - 1858 March 22. Caroline Fiero ALS to Milla Bush; Oberlin, [Ohio], 8 pages; First impressions of college. Describes accommodations, courses, and religious attendance required of Oberlin students. "I never heard of so many prayers in my life as there are offered here. It is prayer after prayer or some kind of religious meeting all the time." Heard about a murderer in a recent letter.
  - 1858 April 1. Josiah Quincy ALS to W[illiam] B. Sprague; Boston, [Massachusetts], 3 pages; Thanks Sprague for sending him the 3rd and 4th volumes of Annals of the American Pulpit. Reflection on meeting Presbyterian minister Dr. John Witherspoon ca. 1792 and hearing him preach. "I was particularly struck with his style & manner in the delivery of his discourse. It was solemn, direct, with no display of oratory, or for effect. Terse... obviously studied, but without full notes, and relying more on his logic than on imagination for the result to be produced." Etc. Description and speaking style of Samuel Stanhope Smith, who presided over the marriage of Quincy and his wife "Excuse erasures & interlineations. At Eighty six the thread of thought breaks in ye weaving and splicing & knotting is unavoidable." [Note: Smith was also author of a sketch of the life of John Witherspoon, published in volume three of Sprague's Annals]
  - [18]58 May 20. Geo[rge] Bancroft ALS; New York, [New York], 1 page; Bancroft writes stating that he will be sending "Page 11" tomorrow. "I give up in despair teaching our stereotypers exactness."
  - 1858 September 14 - 24. Edwin J. Carver ALS to Mr. and Mrs. John Carver; New York City, [New York], 8 pages; Letter to his parents in Norwich, England. Detailed descriptions of New York City and Long Island. Notes the celebration of the completion of the Atlantic Telegraph. Comments on local farms and gardens, their produce, and insects. Discusses the construction of Central Park, "or Central stoneheap as Mr Richards calls it. It may be a park a hundred years hence, but it wont be much before." Mentions various religious services, including a Henry Ward Beecher sermon attacking slavery. Notes the burning of Quarantine Station on Staten Island. Remarks on various newspapers and other publications.